<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Nihongo Naraimashou</string>
    <string name="title_account">Account</string>
    <string name="title_exam">Exam</string>
    <string name="title_report">Record</string>
    <string name="title_lesson">Lesson</string>
    <string name="title_home">Home</string>
    <string name="title_activity_writing">WritingActivity</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="section_format">Hello World from section: %1$d</string>
    <string name="intro1"> Hi welcome to nihongō naraimashō or “let’s learn Japanese language” in English. nihongō naraimashō will teach you how to read and write hiragana, katakana and kanji, it will also teach you the pronunciation.</string>
    <string name="intro2">In Japanese writing system it’s start from right to left(vertical)writing in this application. We will use the western style which is from left to right(horizontal). Japanese sentence don’t use question mark they use “  。” only for any sentence. </string>
    <string name="intro3">Now for writing hiragana and katakana they use small “っ” (tsu) for double consonant for example gakkou “がっこう”  the tsu here is for repeating the  consonant k, same thing with the katakana but in case of “konnichiwa”  you will not write it like こっにちは(note: this is wrong) because in hiragana and katakana there is “ん” or the “n” so you should write it like this こんにちは</string>
    <string name="intro4">From the example above, take a look at the end the “wa” is written as “は” or “ha”, but you will read it as “wa”, this is called particles (preposition). Another example “watashi wa” written as “わたし　は” (note: watashi is a Japanese word so you will not write it as “はたし”=hatashi because it is not a particle). There is also particle like “へ” you write it as “he” but read it as “e” (note: you will encounter this in lesson 5) and lastly, the “を” you write it as “wo” but read it as “o” (note: you will encounter this in lesson 6).</string>
    <string name="lesson1_a">In the vocabulary section you will notice that there is only “1 to 10” only and the number “4,7,9” have two meanings. You will encounter the other use of it on upcoming lessons. </string>
    <string name="lesson1_b">You need only “1 to 10” in Japanese to count up to 99. The trick is simple, for example 11 = 10 + 1  read as “juu ichi”. 20 = 2 x 10 read as “ni juu”, 35 = 3 x 10 + 5 “san juu go”. You need to read it left to right for example, “56” it will be read as “go”(5) then “juu” it is telling how many tens then “roku”(6). Note: for counting use “yon” for “4”, “nana” for “7” and “kyuu” for “9”</string>
    <string name="lesson1_c">Now that you know how to count “1 to 99” you can also tell age from 1 year old up to 99 years old by adding the suffix “sai/さい” number  + sai  = age.  Example:  issai(note: not ichi sai), ni sai, san sai, yon sai, go sai, roku sai, nana sai, hassai(note: not hachi sai), kyu sai, jussai(note: for 20 years old use hatachi). You can see that there are double ss from one year old 8 years old and 10 years old. Number will fall for that number like 11(juu issai), 21(ni juu issai), 88 hachi juu hassai, 78(nana juu hassai), 30(san jussai) and so on you need to use that.   </string>
    <string name="lesson1_d">For the nationality you just need to use the suffix jin together with the country. Example Japanese, “nihon jin”, Korean “kankoku jin”</string>
    <string name="lesson1_e">For the sentence pattern “S wa I desu” where “S” is the subject, “I” is information to the subject and last is “desu” which is “is, are, am. Example: (Mr. Miller is 20 years old.-->Miller san wa hatachi desu.) (Ms. Amata is a teacher.-->Amata san wa sensei desu.)</string>
    <string name="lesson1_f">How about if you’re going to say (Mr. Miller is not 20 years old.--> Miller san wa hatachi ja arimasen/dewa arimasen) the same pattern is apply but you use “ja arimasen” or “dewa arimasen” for “not”</string>
    <string name="lesson1_g">For the sentence pattern for asking or interrogative sentence “S wa Int desu ka” where Int is for interrogatives word(note: particle ka is use for asking questions and this pattern will use thought of the other lessons). Example: nansai, dare, donata, doko, Example. (How old are you? --> anata wa nansai desu ka.) (who are you? --> anata wa dare desu ka.)</string>
    <string name="lesson1_h">Some question are answerable by yes or no. Is mr. miller is 20 years old? Yes mr. miller is 20 years old or no mr. miller is not 20 years old. In this case you just use the hai and iie. </string>
    <string name="lesson1_i">Particles usage(preposition) in this lesson there are two particles which is “no” and “mo” particle no is use for noun modifiers.(note: noun1 no noun2) example mr. miller is a ABC’s trainee. --> miller san wa abc no kenshuusei desu. As for “mo” it means also or too. Example: (mr. miller is a ABC’s trainee. --> miller san wa abc no kenshuusei desu.) Ms. Yamada is also a abc’s trainee. --> Yamada san mo kenshuusei desu(note: that the particle “wa” is change to “mo”)</string>
    <string name="lesson2_a">“Kore” use when the speaker is near the object then the listener is far from the object, “sore” is use when the speaker is far from the object then the listener is near from the object lastly “are” use when both speaker and listener far from the object.</string>
    <string name="lesson2_b">For the sentence pattern “kore, sore, are wa object desu.”. Example: (kore wa hon desu --> this is a book), (sore wa hon desu. --> that is a book), (are wa hon desu. --> that thing over there is a book.) Next is the “desu ka desu ka pattern” which is “or” in English Example: (kore wa hon desu ka zasshi desu ka.) --> is this a book or a magazine?. The kono sono ano is same usage but kono sono ano is always followed by noun. Example: (kono hon wa watashi no desu. --> this book is mine.)</string>
    <string name="lesson2_c">The particle in this lesson is “no” which has two usage telling ownership and telling type, brand, and kind, Example: (kore wa nike no kaban desu --> This is a nike bag) in this sentence it tells brand of a bag. (kore wa yamada san no kaban desu --> This is Mr. Yamada’s bag.)Therefore when asking or the interrogative for this is “nan no” and “dare no”(note: the sentence pattern for interrogatives is in lesson 1 grammar section)</string>
    <string name="lesson3_a">In this lesson is somewhat similar to lesson 2 but this time where going to talk about places. In previous lesson we use kore, sore, are to distinguish position of a speaker and a listener. Here in lesson 3, were going to use koko, soko asoko  cause we are going to talk about places.</string>
    <string name="lesson3_b">For the sentence pattern “koko, soko, asoko wa PLACE desu”, Example: (koko wa toire desu --> here is the toilet. ), (soko wa toire desu --> there is the toilet),  (asoko wa toire desu. --> that place over there is the toilet.) it can be reversible  “PLACE wa koko, soko, asoko desu.” As for asking for country the sentence is “name –san no oku ni wa dochira desu ka.” and for company “name –san no kaisha wa dochira desu ka”</string>
    <string name="lesson3_c">The particle in this lesson is “no” which asking for where the object made from. Example:  (kore wa doko no tokei  desu ka.) clearly is same thing with lesson 2 but the answer with this kind of question is like this (kankoku no tokei desu) “take note of the answer its clearly state the answer is country”. Therefore when asking of the interrogative is doko no asking for where the object made from. Another interrogative here in this lesson is nan gai asking for what floor. You just need to put kai for numbers. (ikkai, nikai, sangai, yonkai, gokai, rokkai, nanakai, hakkai, kyuukai, jukkai). This for 1st floor up to 10th floor.</string>
    <string name="lesson3_d">Another interrogative here is ikura (how much) but since you probably know how to count 1 to 9 this time we are going to learn counting up to millions by using the suffix hyaku, sen and man. </string>
    <string name="lesson3_e">Take note of the red fonts in hundreds and thousands there a specials so you need to memorize them, other than that is simple logic. For ten thousand you just there is no special so just put 1 to 10 then man becomes thousand. Example: (ichi man, ni man, san man, and so on up to  kyuu man. ) using this give you can tell numbers up to 8 digits since Japanese change after 4 digit.  </string>
    <string name="lesson3_f">The trick is simple you need to imagine a line after 4 digits and read it as is and that imaginary line is the “man”  38,37/8,654 -- cut like this and read the 1st 4 digits as is and then as for “/” it’s man then read the last 4 digits. You can study the example give for you to understand it more.</string>
    <string name="lesson4_a">In this lesson is all about days of the week, time, minutes, also adverb of time and introduction to verbs. </string>
    <string name="lesson4_b">Notice that we already use the “shichi” for seven and “ku” for nine in the time. For four there is “yo” not yon. You will also notice that there are single “p” double “p” and “f” for the minutes. If you want to tell am or pm you just put gozen or gogo right before the time. Example: (gozen shichi ji --> 7am, gogo shichi ji --> 7pm) and so on and so fort </string>
    <string name="lesson4_c">Now for the sentence pattern for asking time (ima nan ji desu ka --> what time is it now), sentence pattern for asking time in different location. “Location wa ima nan ji desu ka” Example: (what time is it now in Philippines? --> firipin wa ima nan ji desu ka.). “Establishment wa nan ji kara nan ji made desu ka” Example: (from what time until what time is the bank  --> ginkou wa nan ji kara nan ji made desu ka.) note: when you using kara or made make sure state the time before kara or made.</string>
    <string name="lesson4_d">This time I’m going to teach the verb conjugation in Japanese language. There are four conjugation in Japanese language masu, masen, mashita, masendeshita.</string>
    <string name="lesson4_e">Negative conjugation means that the verb is not done by the subject. The verb in Japanese language is always in the end of the sentence. “what time did you wake up this morning?” --> anata wa kesa nan ji ni okimashita ka. “subject wa adverb of time Verb. Note: that if there is a verb in the sentence there will no more desu in the sentence.</string>
    <string name="lesson4_f">The particles in this lesson is “ni” which use for telling specific time and specific date and particles “to” which is “comma,and” English but this particle is also use for two or more nouns. Example: (Monday, Tuesday and Wednesday --> getsuyoubi to kayoubi to suiyoubi) never use particle “to” between sentences and verbs.</string>
    <string name="lesson5_a">In this lesson is all about using ikimasu, kimasu, kaerimasu. The sentence pattern for this lesson is “subject wa COMPANION to TRANSPORTATION de PLACE e ikimasu, kimasu, kaerimasu. Example: (I will go to japan by airplane with my friend --> watashi wa tomodachi to hikouki de nihon e ikimasu.) it’s not necessary to be in that order, it be ramble like PLACE e COMPANION to TRANSPORTION de ikimasu, kimasu, kaerimasu. It can be in any order just be the right use of particles.</string>
    <string name="lesson5_b">The particle here “to” use for companion which the interrogative is “dare to” asking for companion. Particle “de” which the interrogative is “nan de” which asks the transportation.  Particle “e” which the interrogative is “doko e” ask for place going to, came or returning.</string>
    <string name="lesson5_c">The particle here is “to” use for companion which the interrogative is “dare to” asking for companion. Particle “de” which the interrogative is “nan de” which asks the transportation.  Particle “e” which the interrogative is “doko e” ask for place going to, came or returning.</string>
    <string name="lesson5_d">If you’re going to say “alone” it’s fix for the “hitori de” and as for the “by foot” you don’t need to put particle “de” on it. if you’re going to say you that you don’t go anywhere or didn’t go anywhere “doko mo negative of the verb. “doko mo ikimasen, doko mo ikimasendeshita)</string>
    <string name="lesson6_a">In this lesson is about transitive verb. The sentence pattern for this lesson is “noun を TRANSITIVE VERB” Example: (I will eat breakfast -->わたし　は　あさごはん　を　たべます。Next is telling place of actions “Place of action で noun を TRASITIVE VERB” Example: (I will eat breakfast in the restaurant. --> わたし　は　レストラン　で　あさごはん　を　たべます。</string>
    <string name="lesson6_b">The interrogative for this lesson is なにを asking what, and どこで asking for the place of actions. Just be careful using あいます the particle for that is “に”　ともだち　に　あいます。Then using　それからis right after done with the first action. 　ともだち　に　あいます。それから　うち　へ　かえります。</string>
    <string name="lesson7_a">This lesson is about pair verbs and in this lesson will also tell what tools, language use to execute the certain action.</string>
    <string name="lesson7_b">As for the sentence pattern “tools で noun を Transitive verbs.” Example: (にほんじん　は　はし　で　ごはん　を　たべます。--> Japanese eat meal by chopsticks.) next is “LANGUAGE 1　は　LANGUAGE 2　で　なん　です　か” Example: (Thank you は　にほんご　で　なん　です　か。). Another one is “subject は recipient/from　に　noun　を　あげます” --> Example: (やまぐち　さん　は　ともだち　に　くつ　を　あげます。) same thing with the other verbs here in this lesson. The doer of the action takes the particle “は” while the recipient takes the particle “に”. Lastly “もう　Vました” Example: (もう　レポート　を　おくりました　か。) when answering this type of questions you if you say (“いいえ　まだ　です” you just stating that the doer is not yet done so never answer by ませんでした) (“はい　もう　おくりました。” on the other hand saying yes simple your already done with it.)</string>
    <string name="lesson7_c">For the interrogatives for this lesson “なんで” asking what tool/methods did the doer use in certain action. “だれに”asking from the receiving side as あげます、もらいます and etc, (Example:　フィリピンじん　は　なんで　ごはん　を　たべます　か。), (やまぐち　さん　は　だれに　えいご　を　ならいました　か。)</string>
    <string name="lesson8_a">In this lesson are all about adjectives. There are two type of adjectives in Japanese language we called “i” adjective and “na” adjective. Let me show you first how to conjugate each type before proceeding to sentence pattern.</string>
    <string name="lesson8_b">As you can see there is a really big difference between a “i” adjective and “na” adjective in terms of conjugation. If you look carefully at the “i adj” the last letter “i” is gone and add　“くない” or かった and for the past negative it’s clearly again in the “くない” becomes “くな” only so be careful with that. For the sentence pattern first is “subject は i adj or na adj です。Example: (アメリカ　は　きれい　です。,　ふじさん　は　たかい　です。). If “na adj” follow by a noun you need to put “な” in between them “きれい　な　ひと” and for “i adj” you need to leave it as it. “あたらしい　かばん” </string>
    <string name="lesson8_c">Interrogatives here are どんな, どれ, どう. When you using “どんな” it need to be followed by a noun unlike “どう” it’s just followed by “です　か。” as for “どれ” it’s same use of  “どう”</string>
    <string name="lesson8_d">Particles in this lesson are “な”, “が”, particle “な” using when a “na adj” is followed by a noun. Particles “が” use for contradicting statement. “にほん　の　たべもの　は　たかい　です　が　おいしい　です。” Since the particle “が” means but so you need to use contradicting adjectives but if you have an adjectives that not contradicting to each other you can use “そして”  “にほん　は　しずか　です　そして　きれい　です。” とても and あまり are both adverb of degree. They put before adjectives. When using とてもmake sure it’s in positive and for あまり make sure use negative.</string>
    <string name="lesson9_a">In this lesson is about possession, ability and preferences. Transitive is use by particle “を” here we are going to use particle “が”. Sentence pattern is (Noun が あります/わかります) </string>
    <string name="lesson9_b">You already know the use of どんな here it can also be use but need to be followed by a category. Example: (どんな たべもの が すき です か。--> what kind of food do you like?). There are also several adverb of degree in here. よく/だいたい/すこし/あまり/せんせん can be used in わかります while たくさん/すこし/あまり/ぜんぜん can be used in あります note: remember when using あまり/ぜんぜん the verb/adjectives should be in negative form.</string>
    <string name="lesson9_c">For asking reason you can use “どうして” then make sure state the reason first then put “から”. The “から” here is not “from” but becomes because. “ねつ が あります から かいしゃ を やすみます。” just like the example the reason here is the sentence after the “から” unlike in English after because is the reason.</string>
    <string name="lesson10_a">In this lesson is somewhat connected to “lesson 3”. First let us know what the difference of between “arimasu” and “imasu”. They kind of similar cause they both tells us what is existing in the place but “arimasu” use for inanimate meaning object that cannot move but itself. Example are trees, cars, machine etc. on the other hand, “imasu” use for animate meaning object that can move but itself. Example are human beings, animals, insects and etc.</string>
    <string name="lesson10_b">Sentence pattern Noun が あります/います this sentence pattern tells the existence of an object or presence of thing/s or person/s.</string>
    <string name="lesson10_c">Place に Noun が あります/いますparticle に here emphasize where is the existence of an of object or person</string>
    <string name="lesson10_d">Subject は Place に Noun が あります/います in this sentence pattern the takes a subject and tells where it exists. The subject taken by the speaker need to be both know by the speaker and listener.</string>
    <string name="lesson10_e">Location の specific location に tells the exact location of object or a person.</string>
    <string name="lesson10_f">It’s clear the use of particles here such as に and が. Lesson 4 you learned the use of particle と which means and in English this time in this lesson there is や tells other the said there is something other things in there. Sometimes there is など.</string>
    <string name="lesson11_a">You leaned in previous lesson about telling about existence of object or person, this time we are going identify the numbers of objects or person by adding the right quantifiers for example we use “なんにん” for person. “なんだい” for machine or vehicles and so on and so forth.</string>
    <string name="lesson11_b">As for the interrogatives いくつ is used for general question for “how many” things which counted by ひとつ ふたつ and so on. There is also “どのくらい” for how long</string>
    <string name="lesson11_c">Quantifier に ーかい Verb. This sentence pattern says how often you do the action.</string>
    <string name="lesson11_d">Note: that －かい for floor and －かい for frequency is the same but 3rd floor is さんがい and interrogatives is なんがい while frequency さんかい(thrice) and the interrogative is なんかい</string>
    <string name="lesson12_a">This question asks the listener to choose between two items. Which is noun1 or noun2 the interrogative used is always どちら</string>
    <string name="lesson12_b">Category [の 中] で {なに/どこ/だれ/いつ/} が いちばん Adjectiveです か。Note: [の 中] can be omitted or not.</string>
    <string name="lesson13_a">In this lesson you will learned what you want and another conjugation for verb.</string>
    <string name="lesson13_b">Noun が ほしい です This sentence pattern is used to express the speaker’s desire to possess or have an object. It can also be used to ask what the listener wants. The object is marked with the particle が ほしいis an i adjective.</string>
    <string name="lesson13_c">Vますーformたいです a verb when it is used with ます is called Vますーform. Example かいます,　かい is the ますform. This expresses the speaker’s desire to the certain verb. たい is a i adjective. Using たいform the verb becomes “want” (want to buy かいたい です) (want to drinkのみたい です)</string>
    <string name="lesson13_d">Note: ほしいですor たいです cannot be used to describe third person’s desire. Another thing is neither ほしいですかnor たいですか when you offering something or invite someone to do something. For example you offer a cup of coffee (or invite the listener to have a cup of coffee), you should not say コーヒー は ほしい です か。nor should you say コーヒー を のみたい です か。You should use いかがですか。のみませんか</string>
    <string name="lesson13_e">Place へ Noun/Vますformに いきます/きます/かえりますthis sentence pattern is somewhat similar to lesson 5 but this time you can use this pattern to state the purpose going to a certain place.</string>
    <string name="lesson13_f">About the particle に use for the verb はいります/のります and particle を for でます/おります when entering or riding you should particle に while getting off or getting out you should use particle を</string>
    <string name="lesson14_a">This lesson is about てform of the verb another verb conjugation. There are rules before you conjugate the verb in to てform. Japanese verb divided in to 3 categories which we called group 1, group 2 and group 3.</string>
    <string name="lesson14_b">Note: there are some verbs that appears to be in group I but they belong in this group. i will list done the 13 verbs that i know together with there meaning</string>
    <string name="lesson14_c">This sentence pattern is used to ask, instruct or encourage the listener to do something. Naturally, if the listener is one’s superior, this expression cannot be used for giving instructions to him/her.</string>
    <string name="lesson15_a">In addition to the usage of Vてform います you learned in lesson 14, it is also used in describing a certain continuing state which resulted from a certain action in the past</string>
    <string name="lesson15_b">is also used in describing a habitual action; that is when the same action is repeatedly performed over a period of time. So be careful with the two.</string>

    <!-- TODO: Remove or change this placeholder text -->
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>

</resources>
